Hey there, it's me.
Another day, another useful lesson from prep.
Welcome back to our IELTS writing course.
Before we start, let's participate in a quick activity called, where's the trend?
The rules are very simple.
I will show you a task 1 sample and within 2 minutes,
you need to identify 3 trends in it.
Remember, just identify 3 trends to win.
Are you ready?
3, 2, 1, start!
Oh dear, why is it so challenging right from the start?
Is anyone struggling to figure it out?
Those who can identify all 3 trends in this sample within 2
minutes will receive a tap on the head from me, because this graph has no trend.
If it was a chart showing changes over time, it would cover
at least 2 years or more.
Otherwise, it's just a list of years on the x-axis.
This chart belongs to a completely different type.
It's charts of comparison.
It doesn't have any trend, just comparison.
Are you ready for the new chart type?
Let's do this.
In today's lesson, we will focus on 2 criteria, which are task
achievement and coherence and cohesion.
With the V model, the method of thinking from general to specific
and from specific to general, similar to charts with trends, we will
go through 3 steps of analysis.
The big 3, the great 3 and the major 3.
Let's move on to the first step.
When you don't know where to start, please look at the big
picture, the overview or what we call the big 3, then gradually narrow it down.
The big 3 refer to 3 elements on the chart that immediately catch our eyes.
The title of the chart, the y-axis and the x-axis.
From the title of the chart, we can figure out what, here
is the amount of tea and coffee imported, and where by 4
different countries.
From the y-axis, we have the unit, which is tonnes.
The x-axis is where the biggest difference lies, compared to charts
with trends, instead of a time axis, here we see the names
of 4 countries, with each country having 2 data bars, corresponding to 2 imported items.
We can consider this as a group of information or category.
Please remember the name, so we can analyse the question more easily.
Also, because the x-axis no longer provides information about years, let's
pay closer attention to other details, such as the question or the
chart, to see if the year is mentioned, so that we can
identify the correct tense.
If we look at the chart and title, we see no specific
year mentioned, so we'll use the present simple tense in this sample.
Please write a big present simple right below the chart title to remember.
To sum up, the big 3 provided us with the following information.
Canada, the US, the UK and Germany.
Next is the great 3, including 1.
Subjects of comparison 2.
Global feature number 1 and 3.
Global feature number 2.
Attention!
This is a chart of comparison, it means there are no trends
at all, so do not write the global trend in the overview.
Instead, we'll need a second global feature to have a complete overview,
which will help you improve the task achievement score.
Firstly, subjects of comparison.
This is a bar chart, so the subjects of comparison will correspond
to the subjects that are represented by two different colours in the
chart, which are tea and coffee.
Let's take an overview of this chart.
What are the global features that you see?
Let me remind you, global features should focus on 1.
Comparison – comparing factors such as the highest or lowest subject, or
which group is higher compared to others.
2.
Special points – such as highest, lowest, starting, ending, intersecting points.
So, are there any comparisons or special points that catch your eye right away?
It can be seen that the UK records the highest figure for
tea, while Germany reports the largest level for coffee.
Therefore, the first global feature is, the tea import is highest in
the UK, while coffee is highest in Germany.
And what about the variation, or in other words, the difference in
the import amount between the given countries?
It's obvious that the tea levels vary significantly, jumping from very low to very high.
However, the coffee levels are much more consistent across the countries.
Therefore, the second global feature is, the variation in tea import is
larger than in coffee.
Let's take a look at the big three and the great three
once again.
The last step in the analysis, the major three, goes into the
details, looking at how information is grouped, how paragraphs are divided,
selecting the most important individual features and arranging them in a
logical way to create a complete writing.
Let's remind a bit about the three elements of the major three.
1.
Grouping information.
How to group information, dividing the body into two paragraphs.
2.
Individual features.
Please note that this is a chart of comparison, so there's no
trends, no individual trends, only individual features.
3.
Detail organisation.
Organise the information to describe the chart.
This symbol, I'm sure you still remember it, when dividing paragraphs in
Charts with Trends writing, we can use one of the two methods.
The vertical approach, dividing the chart from top to bottom, or by year.
And the horizontal approach, dividing the chart from left to right, or
grouping by subjects of comparison.
For Charts of Comparison, since there are no trends, the way we
divide paragraphs is slightly different.
To effectively group the information, first, we need to identify what are
being compared here.
We can see that there are at least two comparisons to be made.
1.
Comparisons between categories.
And 2.
Comparisons between subjects of comparison.
Correspondingly, we also have two methods of dividing the body for Charts of Comparison.
1.
Grouping by category.
And 2.
Grouping by subject of comparison.
Follow method 1, we have four categories corresponding to four countries.
The easiest way to group them is to find which categories share
similarities in terms of pattern, which means order of information, or in
terms of data in those categories.
Among the four countries, we see that Canada, the US and Germany
follow a similar pattern.
They all have higher figures for coffee imports compared to tea.
So we could group these three countries into body 1.
And for the UK, which shows the opposite trend, importing significantly more
tea, let's put it into body 2.
Sometimes we should follow method 2, grouping by subject of comparison.
For example, in this chart we are dealing with two distinct commodities, tea and coffee.
Comparing the country's performance for one product at a time is very logical.
So, let's put all the data regarding tea import into one paragraph
and coffee import into the other.
This way we can clearly see which country ranks highest or lowest
for each specific drink.
Generally, both methods are effective, depending on each specific chart.
You should apply whichever method seems easier for you.
There is often more than one effective way to divide body paragraphs,
so you can be confident in your choices and don't worry too much.
For this essay, we will follow method 2, grouping by subject, as
it allows for direct ranking of the countries.
Body 1, tea import.
Body 2, coffee import.
Moving on to the second element in the major three, individual features,
including special points, comparisons and numbers that need to be described in the writing.
Let's find out one by one.
Firstly, let's look at tea import.
The UK records the highest figure, reaching 80,000 tonnes.
This is the most significant feature, and you should describe it in
your writing because it is the only country where the amount of
tea imported is higher than coffee.
Germany follows with 40,000 tonnes.
Note that this is exactly half of the UK's level, which is
a great comparison to make in your report.
Lastly, the US and Canada stand at the lowest positions.
Their data is rather similar, with both countries importing approximately 20,000 tonnes.
Moving on to the second subject, coffee import.
First, Germany imports more coffee than any other country, with 50,000 tonnes.
This is the highest figure for coffee, making Germany the leader in
this category.
Next, we have Canada and the US.
Their levels are neck and neck at around 40,000 tonnes.
It is also notable that in these two countries, the amount of
imported coffee is twice that for tea, a key comparison to mention.
Finally, the United Kingdom ranks last in coffee import, with roughly 30,000 tonnes.
This is a sharp contrast to its tea imports, as this figure
is only about one third of the UK's level for tea.
We've nearly finished the question analysis.
The most important information has been selected.
Now there's just one final step, detail organisation.
It's about arranging the information in each paragraph in a logical way,
so that we can have a complete outline.
Remember, we have two paragraphing methods, grouping by category and grouping
by subject of comparison.
In each paragraph, the rule is to start from the most significant,
the most important information, to the least significant, the least important one.
Hopefully, now you understand how to do it and not feel overwhelmed
by the information in this type anymore.
With such a detailed analysis, you will achieve a band 6 plus
for task achievement and coherence and cohesion.
Using language carefully can lead to even higher scores.
Stay confident, you guys!
A challenging type of chart in task 1 has been handled.
It's so great!
Let me summarise a bit of the knowledge we've covered.
We still analysed charts of comparison through three steps, similar to charts with trends.
The big three, the great three, the major three.
In the big three, as there's no time axis, we identify categories
or groups of information instead of time.
So here's what we have.
1, what and where, 2, unit and 3, category.
The great three also has a small change, with global trend being
replaced by the second global feature, along with subjects of comparison.
Finally, the most significant changes lie within the major three.
1, we don't group information by dividing the chart vertically or horizontally,
like charts with trends, but grouping by category, grouping by subject of
comparison, 2, no more individual trends, only individual features, and 3,
lastly, it's still about organising the information to make a complete outline.
Remember to note down all the do's and don'ts in the checklist.
I know that mastering IELTS writing can be tough, but just by
going in the right direction and doing things correctly, we've already saved
a lot of time and effort.
Keep practising regularly and soon you can master this knowledge, allowing you
to quickly respond in the test room and take control of your writing.
But also remember to rest and eat well to maintain the energy
needed for the ongoing battle ahead.
Take care, everyone.
I'm Anna.
Goodbye and see you next time.